The Lives of the Prophets, Part 1
اَلْحَمْدُ لله ، وَالصَّلَاةُ وَالسَّلَامُ عَلى سَيِّدِنَا محمد وَعَلَى اَلِهِ وَصَحْبِهِ وَسَلِّمْ
They lost in the Battle of dialogue.
They lost up till that moment it was a dialogue between Ibrahim(اِبْراهِيْم) and them.
Whenever the Kuffar(كفار) lose in the battle of dialogue, they don't admit
and they go to the next level and that is actual fighting and physical fighting.
They did that with Muhammadﷺ
Muhammadﷺ had a dialogue with them.
And they were arguing in the beginning and they obviously definitely lost,
you cannot stand against the Hujjah(حجة) of Allah سبحانه تعالى the evidence of Qur'an you can't stand against it.
So when they lost in the field of dialogue, then they resulted to force.
قالوا حَرِّقوهُ
Burn him.
We can't deal with him, we can't debate with him with our minds, burn him.
قالوا حَرِّقوهُ وَانصُروا آلِهَتَكُم إِن كُنتُم فاعِلينَ۝
They said burn him and help your Gods, if you will be doing.
Burn him.
This is an admission of failure.
When they said: Burn him! This is an admission of failure.
It's an admission from their side that they're not able to have a dialogue with him.
They lost, they resulted to force.
It says in the books of Tafseer(تفسير) that they set up a fire it took them days and days to gather the wood for it.
And they set up this trench and they filled it with logs
and they set fire to it and the flames are so high that a bird would fly over it and fall down dead, huge fire.
And they had to throw Ibrahim(اِبْراهِيْم) with a catapult, Manjneeq(منجنيق).
So they put Ibrahim(اِبْراهِيْم) in this catapult and they threw him, in the fire.
Ibrahim(اِبْراهِيْم) landed in the fire.
Fire, which we know burns.
But who's the One, Who created fire?
Allah سبحانه وتعالى
and Who is the One, Who made fire burn?
Allah سبحانه وتعالى.
Are the laws of nature mandatory on Allah سبحانه وتعالى Allah has to follow them.?
Allah is the One, Who created these laws to start with.
So Allah سبحانه وتعالى, who created the fire to burn, can make the fire and air condition.
Ibrahim عليه السّلام landed in this fire, that burns.
Allah سبحانه وتعالى ordered the fire because the fire is a servant of Allah سبحانه وتعالى.
قُلنا يا نارُ كوني بَردًا وَسَلامًا عَلىٰ إِبراهيمَ۝
Oh fire! Be cool and peace, tranquility on Ibrahim(اِبْراهِيْم).
It is said that Ibrahim(اِبْراهِيْم) later, would say
that the most pleasant moments that I had in my life were those moments when I was sitting in the fire.
The best moments that he had in his life the most peaceful moments,
were those moments when Allah سبحانه وتعالى told the burning fire;
قُلنا يا نارُ كوني بَردًا وَسَلامًا عَلىٰ إِبراهيمَ۝
Oh fire! Be you coolness and safety for Ibrahim(اِبْراهِيْم).
Allah سبحانه وتعالى can change everything for you.
Allah made the sun stop, for Yusha Bin Noon(يوشع بن نون),
Allah سبحانه وتعالى made the sea split for Musa(موسى),
Allah سبحانه وتعالى made all diseases vanish under the hand of Syedina Eesa(سيدنا عيسى),
Allah سبحانه وتعالى made the moon split, for Muhammadﷺ,
Allah سبحانه وتعالى made the fire wholeness and safety for Ibrahim عليه السّلام.
Allah سبحانه وتعالى can do whatever He wants for the believer,
we have to have trust in Allah سبحانه وتعالى and Tawakkul(توكل) that Allah will give you victory, if you follow the orders of Allah.
You don't need anything else, you don't need anything.
All what we need is Allah سبحانه وتعالى, all what you need is Allah سبحانه وتعالى,
Subhaan Allah(سُبْحَان الله), and what was the Dua(دُعَا) of Ibrahim(اِبْراهِيْم), when he was thrown in the fire?
حسبي الله ونعم الوكيل
Allah is sufficient for me, Allah is enough, I do not need the help of anyone.
Allah is sufficient for me and He is the best Disposer of affairs.
I do not need anyone but Allah سبحانه وتعالى,
it says in the Hadith(حديث) narrated by Al-Bukhari(بخاريْ), Ibn Abbas(إبن عباس) said;
حَسْبُنَا اللَّهُ ونِعْمَ الوَكِيلُ، قالَهَا إبْرَاهِيمُ عليه السَّلَامُ حِينَ أُلْقِيَ في النَّارِ،
وقالَهَا مُحَمَّدٌ صلَّى اللهُ عليه وسلَّم
حِينَ قالوا: إِنَّ النَّاسَ قَدْ جَمَعُوا لَكُمْ فَاخْشَوْهُمْ فَزَادَهُمْ إِيمَانًا وَقَالُوا حَسْبُنَا اللَّهُ وَنِعْمَ الْوَكِيلُ
Ibn Abbas(إبن عباس) says;
حسبي الله ونعم الوكيل
Allah is sufficient for us and the best disposal of our affairs.
Ibrahim(اِبْراهِيْم) said it, when he was thrown in the fire
and Muhammadﷺ said it, when he was threatened and told that the enemies are gathering for you so fear them
that made them increase in their Eeman(ايمان).
And they said Allah sufficient for us and is the best Disposer of affairs.
When Rasool Allah ﷺ was threatened, that the enemies are mobilizing and gathering to fight you, so fear them
the people were telling Muhammadﷺ to fear the enemy.
Allah سبحانه وتعالى says;
فَزَادَهُمْ إِيمَانًا
that made their Eeman(ايمان) increase.
Allah سبحانه تعالى says;
وَأَرادوا بِهِ كَيدًا فَجَعَلناهُمُ الأَخسَرينَ۝
And they wanted to harm him, but we made them the worst losers,
وَنَجَّيناهُ وَلوطًا إِلَى الأَرضِ الَّتي بارَكنا فيها لِلعالَمينَ۝
Allah سبحانه وتعالى says: And we saved him and Lut(لوط) to the land which we blessed,
and we'll get to that in the Hijrah(هجرة) of Ibrahim(اِبْراهِيْم), later.
After this event happened, the king of Babylon at the time was An-Namrood(ألنمرود).
So An-Namrood(ألنمرود) heard about this young man, who performed this miracle.
Who is he?
Bring him forward.
So they brought Ibrahim عليه السّلام, this young man to debate with the king,
An-Namrood(ألنمرود), the powerful dictator tyrant, An-Namrood(ألنمرود).
So, An-Namrood(ألنمرود) have this debate or dialogue with Ibrahim عليه السّلام.
So Ibrahim(اِبْراهِيْم) told the king, Allah سبحانه وتعالى is the One, Who gives life and the One, Who takes it away.
Can you do that?
And An-Namrood(ألنمرود) said: Yes.
I can give life and I can take it away.
How?
He said: Call two people from jail, call two men from jail.
So they brought these two men from jail.
He commanded his soldiers to execute one of them.
And he told the second one, you're free.
He said: See, I took away the life of this one, and I gave the life to the other one.
Ibrahim(اِبْراهِيْم) didn't mean this foolish, shallow meaning of giving life and death.
Ibrahim(اِبْراهِيْم) was talking about the miracle of life which is occurring in every single moment of the day and night.
Where Allah سبحانه وتعالى is giving life in every single moment of the day and night to a new creature.
That is the meaning that Ibrahim عليه السّلام meant.
Ibrahim(اِبْراهِيْم) is not going to go and argue with the king in this point and this is a pointer in debate.
If you find that the opponent is trying to trap you with an insignificant point or discussion, leave it.
Ibrahim(اِبْراهِيْم) did not respond to this,
Ibrahim(اِبْراهِيْم) completely changed the subject.
And since he saw that this man is stubborn,
and he is going to debate and dialogue with this way, and argue in this fashion, I'm going to get him from another angle.
To close the discussion with him, I'm not going to go down that road with him.
So Ibrahim(اِبْراهِيْم) completely left the issue of life and death alone, even though there's a lot that could be said in it.
But Ibrahim(اِبْراهِيْم) did not debate that point, fine.
He chose another point.
He said;
Allah سبحانه وتعالى brings the sun from the east, bring it from the west.
فَبُهِتَ الَّذِي كَفَرَ
Allah سبحانه وتعالى says; So the disbeliever was utterly defeated, he couldn't speak.
Ibrahim(اِبْراهِيْم) shut him up with this argument.
As I said, this is a pointer to the discussion
because you could have discussed the point of life and death with them and told him;
No, this is not what I meant, what I meant is this and that.
And it would be an endless fruitless discussion.
Ibrahim(اِبْراهِيْم) chose another angle and through an evidence on him that cannot be rebutted.
And he shut him up, that's it.
فَبُهِتَ الَّذِي كَفَرَ وَاللَّهُ لَا يَهْدِي الْقَوْمَ الظَّالِمِينَ۝
And Allah سبحانه وتعالى guides not the people, who are wrongdoers.
I'll read the Ayah(آية) to you.
أَلَم تَرَ إِلَى الَّذي حاجَّ إِبراهيمَ في رَبِّهِ أَن آتاهُ اللَّهُ المُلكَ
إِذ قالَ إِبراهيمُ رَبِّيَ الَّذي يُحيي وَيُميتُ
قالَ أَنا أُحيي وَأُميتُ ۖ
قالَ إِبراهيمُ فَإِنَّ اللَّهَ يَأتي بِالشَّمسِ مِنَ المَشرِقِ فَأتِ بِها مِنَ المَغرِبِ
فَبُهِتَ الَّذي كَفَرَ ۗ وَاللَّهُ لا يَهدِي القَومَ الظّالِمينَ۝
Have you not thought about him, who disputed with Ibrahim(اِبْراهِيْم) about his Lord, Allah.
Because Allah has given him the kingdom.
When Ibrahim(اِبْراهِيْم) said to him, My lord is He, Who gives life and causes death,
he said, I give life and cause death.
Ibrahim(اِبْراهِيْم) said: Verily Allah causes the sun to rise from the east, then causes you to rise from the west.
So the disbeliever was utterly defeated and Allah guides not the people who are Dhalimeen(ظالمين), the wrongdoers.
We can see in this discussion that Ibrahim(اِبْراهِيْم) has a strong level of Yaqeen(يقين),
a strong level of conviction, certainty, in Allah سبحانه وتعالى.
In the issue of life and death, Ibrahim عليه السّلام had Ilm Al-Yaqeen(علم اليقين), certain knowledge.
His knowledge was certain, they cannot shake the man of Ibrahim عليه السّلام in this point.
He knew that Allah is the one who gives life and he knew that Allah was the One, Who takes it away.
But Ibrahim عليه السّلام wants to reach through the level of Ain Ul-Yaqeen(عين اليقين).
Ain Ul-Yaqeen(عين اليقين) is certainty by seeing or witnessing.
Ibrahim(اِبْراهِيْم) had Ilm Al-Yaqeen(علم اليقين), the knowledge of Yaqeen(يقين), the certain knowledge,
but he wants to reach to the level of certain certainty with witnessing or seeing.
So Ibrahim عليه السّلام has no doubts in Allah سبحانه وتعالى
because this argument that he made with the king is based on certain knowledge
you can't argue like that about life and death when your knowledge is shakable or Eeman(ايمان) is shakable.
Sometimes we read the Ayah(آية), the Ayah(آية) that I'm gonna read right now.
And we think that Ibrahim(اِبْراهِيْم) had doubts in Allah.
No! He didn't.
He had Ilm Al-Yaqeen(علم اليقين), certain knowledge,
but he just wants to reach to the level of Ain Ul-Yaqeen(عين اليقين).
Allah سبحانه وتعالى says;
وَإِذ قالَ إِبراهيمُ رَبِّ أَرِني كَيفَ تُحيِي المَوتىٰ ۖ
And remember when Ibrahim(اِبْراهِيْم) said: My Lord, show me how you give life to the dead?
Show me, he wants to see it.
That does not mean that Ibrahim(اِبْراهِيْم) does not believe in it.
Ibrahim(اِبْراهِيْم) does believe in it.
And his argument with the king was based on that belief, but he wants to see it.
So Allah asked him;
قالَ أَوَلَم تُؤمِن ۖ
Allah said: Do you not believe.
Ibrahim(اِبْراهِيْم) said;
قالَ بَلىٰ وَلٰكِن لِيَطمَئِنَّ قَلبي ۖ
He said: Yes! I believe, but to be stronger faith.
I do believe, but I want to be stronger faith.
So Allah سبحانه وتعالى told Ibrahim عليه السّلام take birds, four birds.
slaughter them, chop them into pieces, grind them, not ground beeds, ground birds.
Grind them together.
Mix these four Birds together, mesh the flesh, so it's inseparable.
And then split this mixture into four parts and put one part on the top of a mountain.
So you have four mountains, a quarter of this ground birds, put the quarter of it on a top of a mountain
and then call them.
So Ibrahim(اِبْراهِيْم) put these four quarters of ground bird on the tops of these four mountains.
And then he called them, he said: Come.
All of these birds came together alive, four birds.
So Ibrahim(اِبْراهِيْم) witnessed the miracle of life in front of his eyes.
Allah سبحانه تعالى says;
وَإِذ قالَ إِبراهيمُ رَبِّ أَرِني كَيفَ تُحيِي المَوتىٰ ۖ
قالَ أَوَلَم تُؤمِن ۖ
قالَ بَلىٰ وَلٰكِن لِيَطمَئِنَّ قَلبي ۖ
قالَ فَخُذ أَربَعَةً مِنَ الطَّيرِ
فَصُرهُنَّ إِلَيكَ
ثُمَّ اجعَل عَلىٰ كُلِّ جَبَلٍ مِنهُنَّ جُزءًا
ثُمَّ ادعُهُنَّ يَأتينَكَ سَعيًا ۚ
وَاعلَم أَنَّ اللَّهَ عَزيزٌ حَكيمٌ۝
And remember what Abraham said;
My Lord, show me how You give life to the dead.
He (Allah) said, Do you not believe?
Ibrahim(اِبْراهِيْم) said: Yes! I believe but to be stronger in faith,
Allah said: Take four birds then cause them to incline towards you.
And then put a portion of them on every hill and call them they will come to you in haste
and know that Allah is Almighty, all Wise.
Ibrahim عليه السّلام made Da'wah(دعوة) to his people.
And after all of his efforts and the miracle of Ibrahim عليه السّلام being saved from the fire.
Nobody believed in Ibrahim عليه السّلام except his nephew.
Allah سبحانه وتعالى says;
فَـَٔامَنَ لَهُۥ لُوطٌ ۘ
Lut(لوط) believed in Ibrahim(اِبْراهِيْم).
Lut(لوط) is the nephew of Sayyedina Ibrahim عليه السّلام,
after all of this effort, after this miracle happening in front of the eyes of this nation,
nobody believed in him except his nephew, Lut عليه السّلام.
And they had to leave.
They had to flee from the persecution and the oppression of their homeland.
They had to give up the land of their birth and the land where they were raised up and go and find another land to worship Allah سبحانه وتعالى.
Allah سبحانه وتعالى says;
وَقالَ إِنّي مُهاجِرٌ إِلىٰ رَبّي ۖ
إِنَّهُ هُوَ العَزيزُ الحَكيم۝
I will immigrate for the sake of my Lord.
Verily he is the Almighty the all Wise.
Where was Ibrahim عليه السّلام heading.?
Allah سبحانه تعالى says;
وَنَجَّيْنَٰهُ وَلُوطًا إِلَى ٱلْأَرْضِ ٱلَّتِى بَٰرَكْنَا فِيهَا لِلْعَٰلَمِينَ۝
Allah سبحانه وتعالى says;
And we rescued him and Lut(لوط) in english LOT, to the land which we have blessed for the mankind for the world.
And the blessed land is the Holy Land Ash-Sham(ألشَّام) which is composed today of four countries
because everything in the Muslim world has split up, in the past, that was Ash-Sham(ألشَّام).
Now it is Syria, Falastine(فلسطين), Lebanon and Jordan.
And the center of it all and the holiest of it, is Jerusalem Bait-Ul-Maqsad(بيت المقدس).
This is their direction, Sayidina Ibrahim عليه السّلام was heading for.
On the way he passed through a land called Harran(حرَّان) in Ash-Sham(ألشَّام).
And the people of Harran(حرَّان) used to worship, the stars.
They had a very pretty flexible religion.
They would go out at night at nighttime,
and they would look at the sky and everyone will make a choice and pick a star and they would worship
that was their Ibadah(عبادة)
somebody would worship Venus, someone other would worship another star.
That's how their religion was, it's not very different of what we think of as modern religions today.
Ibrahim عليه السّلام had his own way of Da'wah(دعوة).
Subhaan Allah(سُبْحَان الله) had his style of Da'wah(دعوة).
You remember how he made his Da'wah(دعوة), to his people?
He went and destroyed all of the idols and then he hang the axe on the biggest idol.
Ibrahim(اِبْراهِيْم) over here, how is he making Da'wah(دعوة) to these people?
He went out with them at night.
They went out to worship.
The first star that comes up is not the star it's a planet.
And that is Venus, it is the first star that shines in the sky after sunset.
It looks like a star but it's not it's Venus, the planet Venus.
Ibrahim عليه السّلام said: This is my God.
فَلَمّا جَنَّ عَلَيهِ اللَّيلُ رَأىٰ كَوكَبًا ۖ قالَ هٰذا رَبّي ۖ
When the knight covered him over with darkness he saw star he said this is my Lord,
in front of everyone he said, This is my Lord and then the planet set, he said;
فَلَمّا أَفَلَ قالَ لا أُحِبُّ الآفِلينَ۝
I do not like those that set.
This cannot be my God because it sets.
And then he saw the moon.
The next day he said: The moon is my Lord.
فَلَمّا رَأَى القَمَرَ بازِغًا قالَ هٰذا رَبّي ۖ
He saw the moon, he said this is my Lord
and then the moon set.
So he said;
فَلَمّا أَفَلَ قالَ لَئِن لَم يَهدِني رَبّي لَأَكونَنَّ مِنَ القَومِ الضّالّينَ۝
Unless my Lord guides me, I shall surely be among the err on people.
So he said: In front of everyone, if Allah does not guide me, I'm gonna be one of those who are misguided.
And then the sun came up,
فَلَمّا رَأَى الشَّمسَ بازِغَةً قالَ هٰذا رَبّي هٰذا أَكبَرُ ۖ
This is my lord it's the biggest.
And he pretended that he's worshipping the sun, and then the sun set.
And then finally, Syedina Ibrahim(سيدنا اِبْراهِيْم) said;
فَلَمّا أَفَلَت قالَ يا قَومِ إِنّي بَريءٌ مِمّا تُشرِكونَ۝
إِنّي وَجَّهتُ وَجهِيَ لِلَّذي فَطَرَ السَّماواتِ وَالأَرضَ حَنيفًا ۖ وَما أَنا مِنَ المُشرِكينَ۝
I'm indeed free from all that you join as partners in worship with Allah.
Verily, I have turned my face towards Him, Who has created the heavens on Earth, Haneefah(حنيفة).
Haneefah(حنيفة) is on the straight path.
And I am not of those who are Mushrikeen(مشركين), the ones, who associate other gods with Allah.
So Ibrahim(اِبْراهِيْم) is doing this presentation in front of everyone.
Now there are some Mufassireen(مفسرين) who tend to think that in these Ayaat(آيات) Ibrahim(اِبْراهِيْم) was searching for the truth.
So they give the explanation that Ibrahim(اِبْراهِيْم) did not know the truth, and he was searching for the truth.
And in the end, his search for the truth, led him to worship Allah.
So in the beginning Ibrahim(اِبْراهِيْم) started worshiping Venus and then he worshipped the moon and then he worshipped the sun.
Finally, Ibrahim(اِبْراهِيْم) knew the truth and he worshiped Allah سبحانه وتعالى.
But Al-Mufassir(ألمفسر) Ibn Kathir(اِبْنِ كَثِيْر) strongly disagrees with this.
He says this cannot be true.
He said: We cannot expect from a Nabi(نَبِي) of Allah سبحانه وتعالى to be misguided to worship the sun and the moon and planets.
He said: If Allah سبحانه وتعالى has created the human being on Fitrah(فطرة) of Islam, if that's the original creation,
how could a Nabi(نَبِي) of Allah be misguided so bad that he would worship these stars and planets and not know the truth.
And he mentioned some other evidences to refute this claim that this is a story of Ibrahim(اِبْراهِيْم) searching for the truth.
He says: No.
This was a Da'wah(دعوة) presentation that Ibrahim(اِبْراهِيْم) was giving to the people.
And he said: This comes after the Da'wah(دعوة) of Ibrahim(اِبْراهِيْم) to his own homeland.
This comes after, because after Ibrahim(اِبْراهِيْم) left, then he went to Harran(حرَّان)
and in Harran(حرَّان), the people used to worship the planets, not in the homeland of Ibrahim(اِبْراهِيْم),
in the homeland of Ibrahim(اِبْراهِيْم), they used to worship the idols.
So after he moved out of Iraq, and he got to Harran(حرَّان), he saw the people worshipping these planets,
then he started giving them this presentation.
Also Ibn Kathir(اِبْنِ كَثِيْر) says that
the Ayah(آية) that comes before these Ayaat(آيات) that I recited to you,
clearly shows that Ibrahim عليه السّلام was already given the guidance by Allah سبحانه وتعالى.
And this Ayah(آية) is Allah سبحانه وتعالى says;
وَكَذٰلِكَ نُري إِبراهيمَ مَلَكوتَ السَّماواتِ وَالأَرضِ وَلِيَكونَ مِنَ الموقِنينَ۝
Allah سبحانه وتعالى says, thus did we show Ibrahim(اِبْراهِيْم) the kingdom of the heavens and the earth,
that he may be of those who have faith with certainty.
This Ayah(آية) is before the Ayaat(آيات) that we are talking about worshipping the sun, and the moon, and the stars.
In this Ayah(آية) Allah سبحانه وتعالى is saying that we have shown Ibrahim(اِبْراهِيْم), the kingdom of the heavens and the earth,
so that he can be of those, who have faith with certainty.
Meaning that Allah سبحانه وتعالى has disclosed to Sayidina Ibrahim عليه السّلام some Ilm(علم), some knowledge of the heavens and the earth,
that other people don't have,
and this special knowledge that Allah سبحانه وتعالى has disclose to Ibrahim(اِبْراهِيْم) would elevate him to the level of Moqin(موقن), certain faith.
How can we then say that Ibrahim(اِبْراهِيْم) was searching for the truth?
The word Muhajah(محاجة) or Hajahoo(حاجه) means they debated with him.
We find that this word was not used with any other prophet more than Ibrahim عليه السّلام in Qur'an.
Ibrahim(اِبْراهِيْم) was continuously in debates and dialogues with others about Islam.
He made a debate and a dialogue with the king.
He made the dialogue with his people.
And over here, he's making this debate and dialogue with the people of Harran(حرَّان).
Allah سبحانه وتعالى says;
وَحاجَّهُ قَومُهُ ۚ
قالَ أَتُحاجّونّي فِي اللَّهِ وَقَد هَدانِ ۚ
وَلا أَخافُ ما تُشرِكونَ بِهِ إِلّا أَن يَشاءَ رَبّي شَيئًا ۗ
وَسِعَ رَبّي كُلَّ شَيءٍ عِلمًا ۗ أَفَلا تَتَذَكَّرونَ۝
وَكَيفَ أَخافُ ما أَشرَكتُم وَلا تَخافونَ أَنَّكُم أَشرَكتُم بِاللَّهِ ما لَم يُنَزِّل بِهِ عَلَيكُم سُلطانًا ۚ
فَأَيُّ الفَريقَينِ أَحَقُّ بِالأَمنِ ۖ إِن كُنتُم تَعلَمونَ۝
Wahaajahoo Qaumo(وحاجه قومه), or it could be in general, because Qaumuhoo(قومه) could be referring to his people.
But Ayah(آية) says: His people disputed with him.
He said, Do you dispute with me concerning Allah, while He has guided me,
and I have no fear from those, whom you associate with align worship.
I fear nobody except Allah.
My Lord comprehends in His knowledge, all things, Will you not then remember.
And how should I fear those, whom you associate in worship with Allah,
while you fear not that you have joined in worship with Allah, things for which He has not sent down to you any authority?
So which of the two parties has more right to be in security?
If you but know.
Ibrahim(اِبْراهِيْم) is saying: Why should I fear your gods?
When I have Allah with me?
You are the ones, who should be afraid.
This could seem to be a regular statement.
What's the big deal about it?
But think about it in the right context.
Ibrahim عليه السّلام was one and he's facing the whole and he's telling them I'm not afraid of you.
And I'm not afraid of your threats.
And I have no fear of your gods.
Because Allah سبحانه وتعالى is with me.
Imagine, you standing alone against the nation.
It's not simple.
Facing the whole society telling them I'm not afraid of anything.
I have no fear of your Gods no fear of your threats, do whatever you want.
And then he is not only telling them I don't have any fear, He is telling them I feel very, very secure.
And you should feel insecure.
Because Allah سبحانه وتعالى is on my side, and you have no one to help you and support you.
And then Allah سبحانه وتعالى confirms what Ibrahim(اِبْراهِيْم) has said.
Allah سبحانه وتعالى says;
الَّذينَ آمَنوا وَلَم يَلبِسوا إيمانَهُم بِظُلمٍ أُولٰئِكَ لَهُمُ الأَمنُ وَهُم مُهتَدونَ۝
It is those, who believe and confuse not their belief with any wrongdoing.
For them only there is security.
Only for them is their security and Allah سبحانه وتعالى says;
and they are a guide.
Allah سبحانه وتعالى will provide peace and security for the believers.
وأنزل سكينته
Allah سبحانه وتعالى has revealed His Sakinah(سكينة), the tranquility on the believers in some of the most critical moments,
in Badr(بدر) and other difficult situations Allah سبحانه وتعالى has given the Momineen(مؤمنين) peace and security and tranquility.
And Allah سبحانه وتعالى is telling us that Allah is the One, Who has given Ibrahim(اِبْراهِيْم) that Hujjah(حجة), that ability to debate.
وَتِلكَ حُجَّتُنا آتَيناها إِبراهيمَ عَلىٰ قَومِهِ ۚ
نَرفَعُ دَرَجاتٍ مَن نَشاءُ ۗ إِنَّ رَبَّكَ حَكيمٌ عَليمٌ۝
And that was our proof, which we gave Ibrahim(اِبْراهِيْم) against his people
we raise whom we will in degrees, certainly your Lord is all Wise all Knowing.
Ibrahim(اِبْراهِيْم) now made his Hijrah(هجرة) out of Harran(حرَّان).
Subhaan Allah(سُبْحَان الله) Ibrahim عليه السّلامlived the life of Hijrah(هجرة).
So he left Harran(حرَّان) and he went to Egypt.
When he got to Egypt, the news was carried to the king of Egypt at the time,
that there is a man who is accompanying the most beautiful woman.
They were referring to Sara رضي الله عنها.
And this Hadith(حديث) is in Bukhari(بخاريْ).
Rasool Allah ﷺ says: Ibrahim(اِبْراهِيْم) never lied, except three times.
Ibrahim(اِبْراهِيْم) never lied except three times.
And you'll see that these three lies, don't even count as lies.
Two of them are for the sake of Allah and I'm narrating to you the Hadith(حديث).
Two of them,
إثناني منها في ذات الله
Two of them are in the sake of Allah.
When he said;
إني ثقيم
and when he said;
بل فعلهم كبيرهم هذا
when Ibrahim(اِبْراهِيْم) said: I am ill, I am sick and when he said, the big one, is the one who did it.
You remember when we talked about the people of Ibrahim(اِبْراهِيْم) that they would go out
they had this special night in which they would, they would leave, their town and go out and celebrate.
All the town they would leave, they would vacate the whole town, they would all go out and celebrate.
So they wanted Ibrahim(اِبْراهِيْم) to come with them.
But Ibrahim(اِبْراهِيْم) had the plan, he wanted to stay behind because he had the plan in mind.
But he can't stay behind except if he has an excuse.
So they told them: Why aren't you coming with us?
He said: I'm sick.
What they understood is that he's physically ill.
What Ibrahim(اِبْراهِيْم) meant inside is that he is sick of what they're doing.
So that's a lie because he meant something other than what they understood.
The second lie is
when Ibrahim(اِبْراهِيْم) destroyed all of the idols, he hang the axe on the big idol.
And then when they came back and said: Who is the one, who destroyed the idols?
Ibrahim(اِبْراهِيْم) said: He did.
Now, obviously, Ibrahim(اِبْراهِيْم) knows that he's not the one, who did it.
But Ibrahim(اِبْراهِيْم) wants to drive a point home.
He wants to tell them go and talk to your Gods go and seek help from them.
If they can do you any help.
So these are the two that were done in the sake of Allah.
The third one.
When the king was told that there's a very beautiful woman accompanying Ibrahim عليه السّلام - Sara(سارة).
They wanted to take away Sarah(سارة) from Ibrahim(اِبْراهِيْم) and give her as a slave to the King.
They came to Ibrahim(اِبْراهِيْم) and they asked him: they said: Who is this woman with you?
He said: This is my sister.
He didn't say: She's my wife.
If he said that she's his wife, they would kill him and take her.
Because they don't want the husband of this woman to be alive when she's with the king.
And then he went to Sara(سارة) and told her;
Listen; There's nobody on the face of the earth, believer, except me and you.
And they have came and asked me, What is your relation to me?
I said, You're my sister.
So do not disapprove me.
Tell them you're my sister.
So they came to Sarah(سارة) and said;
What is your relation with this man?
She said: He's my brother.
They took Sarah(سارة).
And they took her in to meet the king.
And the king wanted to place his hand on her.
She made a Dua(دُعَا) to Allah سبحانه وتعالى.
And said: O Allah take care of him.
His hands was paralyzed.
So he told her: Ask your God, Ask Allah to heal me and I will leave you alone.
So she made a Dua(دُعَا) to Allah سبحانه وتعالى to heal him.
So his hand was moving again, he extended it again.
He betrayed his words, he didn't keep his promise.
She made a Dua(دُعَا) another time, his hands was paralyzed another time.
He said: Make a Dua(دُعَا) for me. She made a Dua(دُعَا) for him, a second time.
And his hand was released.
He tried to grab her for the third time.
He requested the Dua(دُعَا), she made the Dua(دُعَا) for him.
His hand was freed.
He said;
إنَّما جئتموني بشيطان
You have not presented me with a human woman.
You have presented me with a devil.
He let her go,
not only that, but to ward off her evil as he thought, he gave her a gift.
He gave Sarah(سارة) a gift our mother Hajar(هَاجَر) as a slave.
Sarah(سارة) now went back to Syedina Ibrahim(سيدنا اِبْراهِيْم) and she had this gift with her, Hajar(هَاجَر).
And that is the story of Sayiditina Hajar(سيدتنا هَاجَر).
In Sahi Al-Bukhari(صحيح ألبخاريْ), it mentions that Ibrahim عليه السّلام circumcised himself,
he received the commandment of Allah سبحانه وتعالى to fulfill this Sunnah(سنة) of Fitrah(فطرة).
And Ibrahim(اِبْراهِيْم) did it, when he was over 80 years old.
He circumcised himself without any anesthesia, without any painkiller, he did it himself
immediate following of the commandments of Allah سبحانه وتعالى, even though he was over the age of 80.
And at up to that moment, Ibrahim عليه السّلام had no children.
He reached the age of 80, No believers, no children, leading a lonely life.
He is patient - Sabr(صبر).
Sarah(سارة) told Ibrahim عليه السّلام that you can have Hajar(هَاجَر) as a wife.
Sarah(سارة) is the one, who gave Ibrahim(اِبْراهِيْم) a permission.
So Ibrahim(اِبْراهِيْم) married Hajar(هَاجَر) with the hope that they would have a child.
And then Ibrahim(اِبْراهِيْم) was given the Bishara(بشارة) of Ghulam Haleem(غلام حليم).
Allah سبحانه وتعالى has described Ismail عليه السّلام with helm(حلم)
which is mild and gentle and forbearing.
While Is'haq عليه السّلام has been described in Qur'an as Aleem(عليم), knowledgeable.
So the Ayaat(آيات) that say: Ghulam Haleem(غلام حليم), a forbearing, mild, gentle child are talking about Ismail(اِسْماعِيْل)
and the Ayaat(آيات) that say: Ghulam Aleem(غلام عليم), knowledgeable child, are the Ayaat(آيات) talking about Is'haq عليه السّلام.
There's an interesting verse in the Bible that I want to recite to you
because it not only gives the glad tidings of Ismail(اِسْماعِيْل), but it goes even further.
This verse in the Bible is in Genesis 1720.
It says, and as for Ismael, I have heard thee,
Behold, I have blessed him, and will make him fruitful, and we'll multiply him exceedingly.
12 princes, shall he beget, and I will make him a great nation.
So the Bible is saying that Ismail(اِسْماعِيْل) is blessed,
and that Allah سبحانه وتعالى will multiply his children and his children are the Arabs
and 12 princes, out of the descendants of Ibrahim(اِبْراهِيْم) will be 12 princes.
There is a Hadith(حديث) where Rasool Allah ﷺ says;
There will be on this Ummah(امة) twelve(12) Khulafaa(خلفاء) all of them are from Quraish(قُرَيْشْ)
12.
And Quraish(قُرَيْشْ) are from the direct descendants of  Ismael عليه السّلام.
And this verse in the Bible is talking about 12 princes
and the 12 princes are 12 Khulafaa(خلفاء).
Four of them are already past Abu Bakr(ابوبكر), Umar(عُمَر), Uthman(عثمان) and Ali(علي).
Some would include Umar Bin Abdel Aziz(عمربن عبدالعزيز), for sure we know about the four and then Al-Mahdi(ألمهدي) is one also.
And there are a few others left.
Not only is the Bible giving us the glad tidings of Ismail(اِسْماعِيْل),
but it's also talking about the 12 Khulafaa(خلفاء) that will rule on this Ummah(امة).
If we have only four or five or six of the Khulafaa(خلفاء) that passed
we have more than half left and that's the good news for this Ummah(امة).
In Fath-Al-Bari(فتح الباري), the commentary of Al-Bukhari(بخاريْ) by Imam Ibn Hajar Al-Asqalani(إمام إبن حجر ألعسقلاني), he says that
when Ibrahim(اِبْراهِيْم) carried his young child and Hajar(هَاجَر) in their Hijrah(هجرة), Ismail(اِسْماعِيْل) was about two years old of age.
Ibrahim عليه السّلام commanded his wife Hajar(هَاجَر) to accompany him in a long trip.
So they started this long traveling, Ibrahim(اِبْراهِيْم) and his wife Hajar(هَاجَر) and their young child Ismail(اِسْماعِيْل).
And then suddenly in the middle of nowhere, desert, dry, barren in fertile desert,
no settlements, no people, no houses, no villages, nothing in the middle of nowhere Ibrahim(اِبْراهِيْم) stopped
and he told his wife Hazel and her son to stay there.
And he left with them a sack filled with dates.
And he left to them some water.
Hajar(هَاجَر) couldn't believe what's happening.
How could we be left over here in the middle of nowhere desert?
So, she followed Ibrahim عليه السّلام.
Are you going to leave us here?
Who are you going to leave us with?
There's no plants, there's no people, there's nothing.
And Ibrahim(اِبْراهِيْم) was not answering, and he's walking away, he didn't even look back.
And she repeated the question Who are you going to leave us with?
He's walking away.
She's following him.
Ibrahim(اِبْراهِيْم), how are you going to leave us here, there's nothing here there's no people.
And Ibrahim(اِبْراهِيْم) was completely ignoring her and not even looking back.
Then finally she asked him a question.
She said: Is this a commandment from Allah سبحانه وتعالى.
Finally, Ibrahim عليه السّلام responded and said: Yes.
Sayidit'na Hajar(سيدتنا هاجر) said;
إذن لن يضيعن الله
Then Allah سبحانه وتعالى will not neglect us.
That's it.
She didn't talk with him further.
Allah told you to do this? Yes.
Allah سبحانه وتعالى will take care of us, He will not neglect us.
This is the Eeman(ايمان) of this mother - Hajar(هَاجَر) - the mother of Rasool Allah ﷺ.
This is her Eeman(ايمان).
She's in the desert, dry desert, no one is there.
She doesn't even have enough food.
All what she have is dates and water, something that we would complain about.
If we're told to live on for one day not to make a living off water on dates.
And her husband is leaving her alone, a helpless mother.
Hajar(هَاجَر) sat down, she would breastfeed him and she would eat from that dates.
Drink from the water, until she ran out of dates and ran out of water and ran out of milk.
Now Syedina Ismail عليه السّلام is crying and weeping
and Rasool Allah ﷺ described him and said;
يتلوَّأ
He was curling.
Ismail(اِسْماعِيْل) was curling on himself because of the hunger.
And he was hitting the ground with his feet.
And he was crying as if he was dying.
At that moment, Hajar(هَاجَر) could not sit down any further.
Even though there's nowhere to go, but she couldn't handle seeing her child dying in front of her eyes.
So she went on top of a mountain that was close to her, she climbed that mountain.
And that mountain was As-Suffa(ألصفاء)
and she looks on top of the mountain if she can see anyone.
She saw no one.
She walk down the mountain, and then she ran through the valley.
And then she climbed another mountain.
The name of that mountain is Al-Marwa(ألمروة).
She got to the top of the mountain, looking around if she can see anyone she saw no one.
So she was down the mountain ran through the valley climbed on As-Suffa(ألصفاء) again.
And she kept on doing that for seven times.
And that is the Sunnah(سنة) of Sayiditna Hajar(سيدتناهَاجَر) that we are doing today in Hajj(حَجْ).
Every one of us is making that site.
Subhaan Allah(سُبْحَان الله), Sayiditna Hajar(سيدتناهَاجَر) at that moment, was afraid, had fear in her heart, she was running with worry.
If she knew what will happen, she would be climbing those mountains with a big smile on her face.
If she knew that the nations of the world, millions and millions of them are going to follow her tracks
and follow her Sunnah(سنة) and follow her way, she would be making that trip with a big smile on her face.
And this is the Rizq(رزق) that Allah سبحانه وتعالى gives to you from the doors that you don't expect.
وَمَن يَتَّقِ اللَّهَ يَجعَل لَهُ مَخرَجًا۝وَيَرزُقهُ مِن حَيثُ لا يَحتَسِبُ ۚ
If you have Taqwa(تقوى) of Allah سبحانه وتعالى,
Allah سبحانه وتعالى will provide for you Rizq(رزق) from places you never expect.
When she got on top of Al-Marwa(ألمروة), and that's the end of the seventh showed, the seventh climbing.
She heard the voice.
She said - ساة - quite,
who she's speaking to.
She's speaking to herself out of confusion.
She's telling herself, Be quiet.
And then is trying to listen.
She heard the voice again, she said;
لقد أسمعت إن كان لديك غواة
If you have any help, I'm able to hear you. Where are you?
And then she looked around to see in the spot where Ismael عليه السّلام was laying down.
The child, the two year old child, the helpless child, the child that is crying, helpless.
She saw an angel, leader of the angels, Jibreel عليه السّلام descended, especially
to that spot where Ismael عليه السّلام was laying down
and Angel started picking up, the dirt with his wink or with his foot, until water started flowing from the ground.
Rizq(رزق) of Allah that came for a helpless child.
So she came down, Sayiditna Hajar(سيدتناهَاجَر).
This water of Zam-Zam(زمزم) came out through divine will of Allah سبحانه وتعالى
a commandment to the angel Jibreel(جِبْرِيْل),
when the water was coming out with the will of Allah سبحانه وتعالى
Sayiditna Hajar(سيدتناهَاجَر) intervene by making a pool around the water.
Because this water was coming out in a desert,
so she thought that this water is gonna flow on the sand and go into Earth and she's not gonna see it.
She intervenes and she started saying them Zam-Zam(زمزم), Zam-Zam(زمزم)
and she's collecting dirt around it to make a pool.
Rasool Allah ﷺ says: If Hajar(هَاجَر) would have left it alone, it would have been a flowing river.
She intervened in it, if she would have left alone it would have been a flowing river,
but she intervene and it became the well of Zam-Zam(زمزم).
Now Sayiditna Hajar(سيدتناهَاجَر) has water,
but she doesn't have food, and she doesn't have company.
So she still needs the social needs and psychological needs.
There was a tribe called Jurhum(جرهم), an Arab tribe, Bedouins traveling in that area.
They saw in the sky, birds hovering, birds in the desert means water.
They said: We know that there's no water over there. So what are these birds doing?
فارسلو جريً أو جريين
All of this that I'm mentioning to you is from long Hadith(حديث) in Bukhari(بخاريْ).
So they sent one or two men to go and investigate.
So the men went rushing.
They came back with the good news that there's water in the middle of the desert,
this group of Jurhum(جرهم), they moved towards the source of water.
And they came there, they arrived there to find this woman and her child.
So they asked a strange question and they got an even stranger answer.
Their question was, would you allow us to camp here?
Would you allow us to camp here?
What is strange about this?
These are a group of men, fighters in the middle of the desert, taking permission from a woman and her child.
If they wanted, they could have eliminated her with a move of a hand.
With a strike of a sword, she could have been over with.
But they were very noble.
So they came and asked her that strange question, would you give us permission to stay here?
Because in the desert, if you have water, that's where you want to be.
And they got a strange answer.
She said;
Yes! But you have no rights in the water, the water belongs to us.
And what's strange about that answer,
the strange thing about it, is that she is in no position to negotiate and bargain.
And nevertheless she is saying;
You have no right in the water, if you want to stay here, you have to stay on our terms, the water belongs to us.
But they accepted, they said: Yes, we agree.
And that is how Jurhum(جرهم) came to stay in that area.
And this is the beginning of the settlement.
Now let me go back when Ibrahim عليه السّلام left Hajar(هَاجَر) and her son in that spot.
Ibrahim(اِبْراهِيْم) walked away, until he got to As-Saniya(ألثنية).
And he made Dua(دُعَا) for them.
It's not easy for a father, very old to leave his only son and his wife in the middle of nowhere, it's not easy.
We do not feel safe leaving our families alone in settled, established secure areas.
It wasn't easy for Ibrahim(اِبْراهِيْم) to leave.
So he stopped and made Dua(دُعَا) to Allah because that is who we seek help from.
إِيّاكَ نَعبُدُ وَإِيّاكَ نَستَعينُ۝
We seek help from no-one but Allah.
And he made a Dua(دُعَا).
What was the Dua(دُعَا) of Ibrahim(اِبْراهِيْم).
He said;
رَبَّنا إِنّي أَسكَنتُ مِن ذُرِّيَّتي بِوادٍ
بِوادٍ غَيرِ ذي زَرعٍ عِندَ بَيتِكَ المُحَرَّمِ
رَبَّنا لِيُقيمُوا الصَّلاةَ فَاجعَل أَفئِدَةً مِنَ النّاسِ تَهوي إِلَيهِم
فَاجعَل أَفئِدَةً مِنَ النّاسِ تَهوي إِلَيهِم وَارزُقهُم مِنَ الثَّمَراتِ لَعَلَّهُم يَشكُرونَ۝
O Allah; I have left my descendant, my family in a valley that is barren and dry in fertile no rain, no trees can grow in that place.
Why?
لِيُقيمُوا الصَّلاةَ
so that they may establish prayer.
In that moment of difficulty, in that moment which we would naturally think about the safety and the food and the drink of my child and my wife,
Ibrahim عليه السّلام is thinking about Salah(صلاة).
Something similar to it because the Sahabah(صحابه) are trained under the head of the Ambiyaa(أنبِيَاء) Muhammadﷺ.
When Rasool Allah ﷺ was talking about Ad-Dajjal(ألدجال)
and Rasool Ullah said that the Ad-Dajjal(ألدجال) will remain among you for 40 days.
One day is equal to a year, one day is equal to a month and then, one day is equal to week,
and the rest of the days are like your regular days.
So one day is equal to a year, the Sahabah(صحابه) had a question about that.
One day is equal to a year what do you think their question was?
I mean, Rasool Ullah was talking about the big Fitnah(فِتْنَه) of Ad-Dajjal(ألدجال)
and he's talking about a day that is equal to a year.
What is the thought that came on the minds of the Sahabah(صحابه)
they said;
هل تكفينا فيه صلاة اليوم
Is it enough for us to pray in that day like this prayer of one day.
The Sahabah(صحابه) are thinking about Salah(صلاة) in the time of Ad-Dajjal(ألدجال).
Rasool Ullah is talking about Ad-Dajjal(ألدجال)
and the Fitnah(فِتْنَه) of Ad-Dajjal(ألدجال) and the Sahabah(صحابه) are thinking about Salah(صلاة).
Anyway Ibrahim(اِبْراهِيْم) said;
لِيُقيمُوا الصَّلاةَ
so that they would establish prayer and then he made the Dua(دُعَا) of the other needs.
We're not saying we don't seek assistance from Allah, to give us Rizq(رزق). No;
We don't say that we don't seek assistance from Allah to provide for us in Duniyah(دُنِيَّا). No;
We ask Allah for that.
But we have to give right proportion,
"رَبَّنَا آتِنَا فِي الدُّنْيَا حَسَنَةً وَفِي الْآخِرَةِ حَسَنَةً"
We asked Allah for Duniyah(دُنِيَّا) and we ask Allah for Aakhirah(آخِرة).
So Ibrahim(اِبْراهِيْم) mentioned the duty of Islam and that is the establishment of Salah(صلاة)
and then he said;
فَاجعَل أَفئِدَةً مِنَ النّاسِ تَهوي إِلَيهِم وَارزُقهُم مِنَ الثَّمَراتِ لَعَلَّهُم يَشكُرونَ۝
So make flocks of people love them and come to them and provide from them fruits.
Subhaan Allah(سُبْحَان الله) that Dua(دُعَا) that was done in the desert, in the empty desert.
Look at the fulfillment of the Dua(دُعَا) of Ibrahim(اِبْراهِيْم).
People are coming from all over the world to that place.
There is no place in the world that is more loved than Makkah.
Because of the attraction that Allah سبحانه وتعالى put in that house.
Allah سبحانه وتعالى has given an amazing description to the house of Allah.
Allah says;
وَإِذْ جَعَلْنَا الْبَيْتَ مَثَابَةً لِلنَّاسِ
Masaba(مَثَابَةً), when the young camel goes to play after it plays for a while it has to go back and see its mother.
Allah سبحانه وتعالى says that the house of Allah is Masaba(مَثَابَةً) you go there, you get stuck.
The love of the house of Allah enters your heart and then when you leave from Makkah, you're always homesick.
You want to go back and see Al-Ka'aba(اَلْكَعْبَه) again.
And that is something that many people describe.
They say that
when we see Al-Ka'aba(اَلْكَعْبَه) for the first time, then that's it, we're hooked to it and we can't leave it for a long time.
Allah سبحانه وتعالى puts the love of this house in the hearts of men, a fulfillment of the Dua(دُعَا) of Ibrahim عليه السّلام.
So the people of Jurhum(جرهم) they stayed there.
And they raised up Ismail(اِسْماعِيْل) and they taught him the Arabic language.
Because Ibrahim(اِبْراهِيْم) was not an Arab neither was Ismail(اِسْماعِيْل), they were from Mesopotamia - in Iraq - the Caledonians.
Jurhum(جرهم), they taught Ismail(اِسْماعِيْل) the Arabic language because he grew up with them.
So he learned the Arabic language,
فاَنفسهم
Rasool Allah ﷺ said: They adored him, they loved him so much.
They married him one of their daughters, and he lived with them.
The mother passed away Hajar(هَاجَر).
And then Ibrahim عليه السّلام would make some visits.
Ibrahim عليه السّلام is traveling always.
So he visited Makkah and he came to the house of Ismail عليه السّلام and he knocked the door.
So, his wife opened the door.
Ibrahim(اِبْراهِيْم) said: Where's your husband?
She said: He's, he's not here.
So Ibrahim(اِبْراهِيْم) asked her: How is your living?
She said: Miserable.
We're having a miserable life, and she complained.
Our food is not good our water is murky and thick and dirty, salty.
So Ibrahim عليه السّلام said;
فأقرئي منِّي السلام، وقولي له: يغير عتبة باب
Deliver my Salaams to him, he didn't even tell her, who he is.
He said: Deliver my Salam to him and tell him to change his doorstep.
Ismail(اِسْماعِيْل) came home and Rasool Allah ﷺ says: As if he felt something.
Subhaan Allah(سُبْحَان الله) he felt that his father was there.
He didn't see him and his wife, she didn't even say anything,
and he asked his wife, did anybody visit us?
She said: Yes. An old man came and he asked about you.
And he told me to deliver Salaam to you and to tell you to change your doorstep.
Ismail(اِسْماعِيْل) said that was my father and he's ordering me to separate from you, you're the doorstep.
So go back home! And he divorced her.
People of Jurhum(جرهم) they loved Ismail(اِسْماعِيْل) so much, they married him another wife.
Ibrahim(اِبْراهِيْم) made another trip.
A while later, knocked the door Ismail(اِسْماعِيْل) wasn't there.
So he asked the same questions to the wife.
He said; Tell me about your living.
She said: Al-hamdulillah(ألحمدلله), the best living.
and she praised the lifestyle that they're leading, this simple lifestyle that they were leading, she praised it.
She was happy and content;
أمراة صالحة
righteous woman.
So Ibrahim(اِبْراهِيْم) wanted to get more details.
He said: What food do you eat?
She said: We eat meat.
What do you drink? Water.
That's all what they used to have meat and water, no desserts, no appetizers, no side dish, meat and water only.
So he made Dua(دُعَا) for them and said Allah gives them blessing in their food.
And Rasool Allah ﷺ says they did not have grains at that time they did not know wheat and barley.
If they had it, he would have made Dua(دُعَا) for them, to bless it for them, but he didn't have it at that time.
But he may Dua(دُعَا) to Allah to bless for them, their food.
And then he said: When your husband, comes back, deliver my salaam to him, and tell him to keep the doorstep.
So Ismail(اِسْماعِيْل) came back.
He said: Did anybody visit us?
He said: Yes, an old man came and he's delivering your salaam(سلام) and he is saying; keep your doorstep.
He said that's my father. You are the doorstep and my father is telling me, to keep you.
Allah سبحانه وتعالى says;
رَبِّ هَبْ لِي مِنَ الصَّالِحِينَ۝
This is a Dua(دُعَا) that's Sayidina Ibrahim(سيدنا اِبْراهِيْم) made.
O Allah سبحانه وتعالى give me an a righteous offspring.
Ibrahim عليه السّلام reached to over 80 years old and he didn't have any offspring, he didn't have any children.
And he didn't ask Allah سبحانه وتعالى to provide him with children per say
but he said: Minas Saliheen(من الصالحين) he has to be righteous.
O Allah سبحانه وتعالى give me an a righteous offspring.
Allah سبحانه وتعالى says;
فَبَشَّرناهُ بِغُلامٍ حَليمٍ۝
We gave him the glad tidings of a child, which is Haleem(حليم).
And Haleem(حليم) is gentle and mild and forbearing.
These are the Akhlaq(أخلاق) of Syedina Ismael عليه السّلام
and Ismail(اِسْماعِيْل) grew up away from his father, in Makkah as we mentioned.
And then when Ismail(اِسْماعِيْل) reached to the age
in which he can go out with his father in the age in which he became an adult,
and is able to take responsibilities for himself.
This age which Allah سبحانه وتعالى mentions in Qur'an.
فَلَمّا بَلَغَ مَعَهُ السَّعيَ
Allah سبحانه وتعالى says and when his son was old enough to walk with him.
Means that Ismail عليه السّلام has grew up and now is able to take care of himself and he's able to take responsibilities.
And that is when the father starts seeing himself in his son.
When your son is a child, you raised him up,
but when your son is an adult, then you see the continuation of your life in him
and that is the age which is Ismael عليه السّلام reached.
When Ismail(اِسْماعِيْل) started to go out with his father.
Sayidina Ibrahim عليه السّلام saw dream.
Sayidina Ibrahim(سيدنااِبْراهِيْم) saw a dream and we know that the dreams of the Ambiyaa(أنبِيَاء) are Wahii(وحي).
In that dream Sayidina Ibrahim(سيدنااِبْراهِيْم) was slaughtering his own son.
فَلَمّا بَلَغَ مَعَهُ السَّعيَ قالَ يا بُنَيَّ إِنّي أَرىٰ فِي المَنامِ أَنّي أَذبَحُكَ فَانظُر ماذا تَرىٰ ۚ
Oh my son I see in my dream that I am sacrificing you.
فَانظُر ماذا تَرىٰ ۚ
What do you think, what is your response?
Ibrahim(اِبْراهِيْم) he will fulfill the order of Allah سبحانه وتعالى no doubt,
but he didn't go and Ismail(اِسْماعِيْل) is in his Sleep and suddenly sacrifices his son.
No, he told Ismail(اِسْماعِيْل), he said;
This is the dream that I saw telling me what do you think?
The answer of Sayidina Ismael عليه السّلام should be studied deeply and taken seriously, by the society that we live in.
This society that gives no rights to the parents
in which the children have no morals in the way they deal with their parents
and in the society that would give rights to everyone even to the perverted
but it would give no rights to the parents.
In a society where the state has more authority over your children than you do.
This response of Sayidina Ismail(سيدنااِسْماعِيْل) needs to be studied very carefully.
Sayidina Ismael عليه السّلام said;
قالَ يا أَبَتِ افعَل ما تُؤمَرُ ۖ سَتَجِدُني إِن شاءَ اللَّهُ مِنَ الصّابِرينَ۝
O my father, do what you are commanded to do.
If a parent will tell his child to provide for him, the son or the daughter won't.
And in the end of their life, they're dumped in an elderly house
and Sayidina Ismael عليه السّلام is giving the most valuable thing that he has and that is his life.
It's not a matter of providing for his father material provisions or taking care of some needs of his father.
He's giving his father his life, he's giving away his life.
And again, I say that's important to study by us, the Muslims,
because we are living in a society that gives no rights to parents.
The only group that have no rights are the parents.
They have no rights whatsoever.
They're disposable thing, they just raise up the children, they bear them and they take care of them
and they work for them and they sacrifice for them, and then when the children reach the age of 18,
they have no obligation whatsoever towards these parents, and that is by law.
The parent cannot take anything from their children after they reach the age of 18, by law, nothing.
The child does not have to obey, does not have to provide does not have to take care
because it's an individualistic society.
And it's affecting the Muslims, it's affecting us because we borrow from the environment we live in.
Sayidina Ismail(سيدنااِسْماعِيْل) said do whatever you are commanded to do.
افعَل ما تُؤمَرُ ۖ
Do whatever you're told to do, whatever Allah commanded you to do; Do it.
And then he said;
سَتَجِدُني إِن شاءَ اللَّهُ مِنَ الصّابِرينَ۝
You will find me of those, who are patient In Sha Allah(إنْ شاءالله).
He didn’t say you will find me patient because we cannot guarantee our actions,
we have no guarantee over what we're going to do this moment, let alone in the future.
Everything that we do we need to realize that it's Taufeeq(توفيق) from Allah سبحانه وتعالى.
Allah is the One, Who made it accessible for us.
And that is why we don't say that we're going to do it and put an end to it that way.
No, we said: We're going to do it In Sha Allah(إنْ شاءالله).
And we asked Allah سبحانه وتعالى to assist us in doing so.
And that is why in every Salah(صلاة) we say;
أهدنا الصراط المستقيم
Guide us to the straight path, it's You, Who will guide us.
Without Your help, we cannot do anything, without Your help, we cannot worship You.
And that's why we need to thank Allah سبحانه وتعالى for every good deed that we do,
and then we need to thank Allah سبحانه وتعالى because he allowed us to thank Him.
سَتَجِدُني إِن شاءَ اللَّهُ مِنَ الصّابِرينَ۝
And then Allah سبحانه وتعالى says;
فَلَمّا أَسلَما وَتَلَّهُ لِلجَبينِ۝
Then, when they both submitted themselves and he had laid him on his forehead,
the position Ismail(اِسْماعِيْل) was in, he was laying on the ground, and his father was holding the knife over his neck.
When they were in that position, Allah سبحانه وتعالى described it as follows,
فَلَمّا أَسلَما وَتَلَّهُ لِلجَبينِ۝
When they both submitted
and the word Aslama(أسلما) and Islam(إسلام) comes from the same root,
the root of the word Aslama(أسلما) and Islam(إسلام) is the same thing.
Allah سبحانه وتعالى is saying that the Ismail(اِسْماعِيْل) and Ibrahim(اِبْراهِيْم), they submitted
when they were in that position they were submitting to Allah سبحانه وتعالى.
And that is Islam because Islam is submission to Allah سبحانه وتعالى.
You fulfill the commandments of Allah, even if it's against your will,
even if it's against your desires, even if it's against what you like.
Nobody would want to slaughter his son.
And no son would want his life to be taken away.
But they're doing it as a form of worship Ibadah(عبادة) and that is Islam; submission.
This is the meaning of Islam.
فَلَمّا أَسلَما وَتَلَّهُ لِلجَبينِ۝
When they were in that position, Ibrahim عليه السّلام had the knife on the neck of Ismail(اِسْماعِيْل)
and he started to pass the knife over is neck.
And then Allah سبحانه وتعالى called Ibrahim(اِبْراهِيْم).
Allah سبحانه وتعالى says;
وَنادَيناهُ أَن يا إِبراهيمُ۝قَد صَدَّقتَ الرُّؤيا ۚ
You have fulfilled the dream.
You have fulfilled it, the dream is fulfilled.
And Allah سبحانه وتعالى told him;
إِنَّ هٰذا لَهُوَ البَلاءُ المُبينُ۝
Verily that indeed was a manifest trial.
It was a test for you and you have passed the test.
Does Allah سبحانه وتعالى need the blood of Ismail(اِسْماعِيْل).
Does need the flesh of Ismail(اِسْماعِيْل), does Allah need the life of Ismail(اِسْماعِيْل), Allah doesn't need it.
Allah سبحانه وتعالى says;
وَفَدَيناهُ بِذِبحٍ عَظيمٍ۝
Verily that indeed was a manifest trial and we ransomed him with a great sacrifice.
It was a test from Allah, Allah does not need the blood.
Allah does not need the flesh, Allah does not need to take away the life of Ismael عليه السّلام
this was a test and they both passed in the test.
So Allah سبحانه وتعالى rewarded Ibrahim عليه السّلام with the sacrifice, A ram.
Look at the results of Taqwa(تقوى) it was an action of Taqwa(تقوى) that Ibrahim عليه السّلام did.
Allah سبحانه وتعالى rewarded him for it.
And now we sacrifice in Eid Al-Ad'ha(عيدالأضحى) and Al-Hadie(ألهدي) in Al-Hajj(ألحَجْ), every year following the Sunnah(سنة) Syedina Ibrahim عليه السّلام.
Ibrahim عليه السّلام was told by Allah سبحانه وتعالى or actually the Ayaat(آيات) say;
وَتَرَكنا عَلَيهِ فِي الآخِرينَ۝ سَلامٌ عَلىٰ إِبراهيمَ۝
And we left for him among generations in later times, Salam(سلام).
After this event happened, Allah سبحانه وتعالى says and we left Salam(سلام) for Ibrahim(اِبْراهِيْم) in the generations to come,
and then and what is the representation of that?
What is the representation of the Salam(سلام) Ibrahim(اِبْراهِيْم)?
How is that manifested?
It is in the Tsgahud(تشاهد), that we do in every Salah(صلاة).
We make Salah(صلاة) and Salaam(سلام) on Ibrahim(اِبْراهِيْم) and Muhammadﷺ in every Salah(صلاة).
Allah سبحانه تعالى says;
وَتَرَكنا عَلَيهِ فِي الآخِرينَ۝ سَلامٌ عَلىٰ إِبراهيمَ۝
And we left for him in the generations to come; Peace on Ibrahim(اِبْراهِيْم).
We're asking Allah سبحانه وتعالى  to grant Ibrahim(اِبْراهِيْم) peace and every Salah(صلاة).
Millions and millions of believers all over the world, throughout generations, five times a day and more
are asking Allah سبحانه وتعالى to grant Ibrahim عليه السّلام peace.
صَلَّى الله عَلى سَيَّدِنَا محمد وَعَلى اَلِهِ وَ صَحْبِهِ وَسَلِّم